in this video we're going to go over
some practice problems associated with
young's double slit experiment
so we have a first order bright fringe
and it's observed to be at an angle of
1.5 degrees
when a light with a wavelength of 600
nanometers passes through the two narrow
slits
how far apart are the two slits
well first
let's get a good understanding
of this experiment
so here we have
two narrow slits
and so they're separated by
a distance d
which is what we're looking for in this
problem
and this is going to be the screen
and in part b the screen is 4.5
meters apart so that's l
now if we have some plane waves
passing through
these two slits they're going to form
they're going to diffract around
the two narrow slits and so these two
waves are going to interfere
with each other
and they're going to create a pattern on
the screen
and so the pattern is as follows
at the center
it's going to be very bright so you can
have a very large amplitude
and then as you move away from the
center the amplitude decreases
so you can get something that looks like
that
so at this point we have a maximum value
that's where constructive interference
occurs
and here we have
a minimum value that's where destructive
interference occurs
now constructive interference occurs
when two waves are in phase
and so they add up
to form
a larger wave so that's constructive
interference
destructive inference occurs when two
waves are out of phase
and so they cancel out
now two waves are out of phase if the
wavelengths differ by a half
meaning not the wavelengths but their
relative positions to each other if
their relative positions differ by
half a wavelength
then they will be out of phase and they
will interfere destructively
however if you have two waves that
are separated by distance of one
wavelength
then they will be in phase with each
other
now there's two equations that you need
to know and we're going to derive them
so let's start with this point
we're going to focus on
this point here
so this is one wavelength two
three
and
i didn't quite make it at three so let's
do that again let's say this is one
two
and then three
and then here let's say
this is one
two
three and then four
now
to get to this first fringe where m is
one
this wave requires
one extra wavelength
and so if we turn this into a right
triangle
where this is the hypotenuse
this will be the extra wavelength
and
this distance will be d
so i'm going to redraw that right
triangle
so it looks something like this
here's the hypotenuse this is d
and this is lambda the extra wavelength
that was needed for this wave
to reach
that point
and this is the angle theta
which
this would be theta one
these two angles are equivalent
this would be theta two
but we'll talk more about that later
sine theta is equal to the opposite side
this is opposite to theta
divided by the hypotenuse which is
across the box order by angle
so we have sine theta equals lambda over
d
so if we multiply both sides by d we get
this equation d sine theta
is equal to lambda
now we need to add
m in front of this equation
because it all depends on which fringe
we're looking at
so for the first order fringe m is one
for second order m is two
here for the one at the center m is zero
for this one m is negative one and m is
negative two
because at this point
these two waves
this one
and that one they will differ by two
wavelengths where m is two
here they will differ by one wavelength
so you need to add m in this equation to
make it work
so make sure you remember this equation
d sine theta
is equal to m times lambda
so anytime you're given the angle in
degrees
you may need to use that formula
now there's another equation that we
need to talk about
so going from here to here this is going
to be theta 1 because it's associated
with the first bright fringe
and this is l
so we can draw a triangle
let's say this is theta one
this is l
and let's call this
the distance between
the first bright fringe and the center
y1 and the distance between
the second bright fringe and the center
y2
so this is y1 in this example
tangent theta
is equal to the opposite side divided by
the adjacent side
so it's y1 over l
so that's another formula to know
now
whenever you have an angle in radians
not in degrees
sine theta is approximately equal to
theta
if theta is very small
and the same is true for tangent theta
it's approximately equal to theta
when
theta is small
so therefore we could say that this
formula
simplifies to theta
is equal to y divided by l
and this formula simplifies to this
d theta is equal to m lambda
and we said that theta is y over l
so then replacing theta with y over l we
get this
now i'm going to multiply both sides by
l
so this is the form that you want to
remember
so y which i'm going to write y sub m
because
it's dependent on this number
times d the separation distance between
the two slits
is equal to l
m lambda
so this is the second formula that you
want to write down
make sure you know these two because
these are the two equations we're going
to be using
now let's go ahead and finish this
problem
so part a
how far apart are the two slits
let's make a list of what we know
so we know that theta
is 1.5 degrees
and we also know that
lambda
is 600
nanometers
that's the wavelength
our goal is to calculate the distance
between the two slits
and we have a first order bright fringe
which means that this is first order m
is 1.
so for this first part we don't need
this equation we only need this one
so let's go ahead and use it
so we need to calculate d
theta is 1.5 degrees
m is 1 and lambda is 600 nanometers or
600 times 10 to the minus 9 meters
so 600 times 10 to the minus 9 divided
by sine of one point five
that's equal to
two point two nine times ten to minus
five
meters
and if you divide it by ten to the minus
three
this is going to be .0229
millimeters
so i'm just going to write that here
now let's move on to part b
what is the distance between the first
bright fringe on the screen and the
center if the screen is 4.5 meters away
from the slit
so this is the screen
so here is the first bright fringe
that's where m is equal to one
so we need to calculate this distance
between the first bright fringe and
the center
so basically y1
so let's use this formula
so in this case m is 1
d is basically this value
l
is 4.5 meters
and lambda is still the same it's 600
nanometers
so we just need to use that formula
so it's y1 times d which is
0.0229
times 10 to the minus 3
that's equal to l
times m
times lambda which is 600
times 10 to the minus 9.
so let's multiply six hundred times ten
to minus nine
by four point five
and then divide that result by point
zero two two nine
times ten to minus three
and so y1
is 0.118 meters
or you could say 11.8 centimeters
so that's how far the first bright
fringe
is from the center
go ahead and try this problem
light with a wavelength of 650
nanometers
passes through two narrow slits that are
0.05 millimeters apart
if the screen is 8.5 meters away from
the slits what is the distance between a
third order bright fringe and a central
fringe
so let's start with a picture
so let's say that this is the screen and
it's
8.5 meters away
from the slits
and so this is going to be the central
bright french
there's the first fringe
second
and then the third
so here m is equal to three
and so we want to find out how far the
third fringe
is from the central fringe
and we're given d the distance between
the two slits
so d is .05 millimeters
and then lambda is 650 nanometers
l
is 8.5 meters
and we're dealing with the third order
bright french so ms3
so let's use this formula again
y m times d
is equal to l m times lambda
so looking for y 3
d is 0.05 millimeters
or 0.05 times 10 to the minus 3.
l is 8.5 and then times
m which is 3
times lambda which is 650 times
10 to the negative 9.
so we need to do is take 8.5
multiply by 3 and multiply that by 650
times 10 to the minus 9
and then take that result divided by
0.05
times 10 to negative 3.
and so y 3 is going to be 0.3315
meters away from the central fringe
so that's the answer
or if you want it in centimeters you
could say it's 33.15
centimeters just multiply this by a
hundred
and so that's it for this problem
number three
light with a wavelength of 550
nanometers in air
passes through two narrow slits in water
and we're given the index of refraction
of water
the screen is 3.6 meters away from the
slits
if the fourth order bright fringe is 4.5
millimeters away from the central fringe
what is the separation distance of the
two slits
go ahead and pause the video
feel free to try this problem if you
want to
so we're given the wavelength in air
that's
550 nanometers
we have the index of a fraction
we have the length which is 3.6 meters
away from
the
two slits
and we also have
m we're dealing with a fourth order
bright fringe
so m is four
and
the distance between the fourth french
and the central fringe
is 4.5 millimeters
so that's ym which is y4
so we need to calculate d
so we need to use this formula
y sub m times d
is equal to l m times lambda
so how do we incorporate n in this
problem
you need to know that as light moves
from
a material with a low index of
refraction
to a material with a higher index of
the wavelength of the light decreases
so we need to calculate the new
wavelength of light
using this formula
so it's going to be 550 nanometers
divided by 1.33
and so the wavelength
of light in water
is
413.5
nanometers
so now we can finish the problem
so ym or y sub 4
is 4.5 millimeters or 4.5 times
10 to the minus 3 meters
our goal is to calculate d the
separation distance of the two slits
l the distance between the screen and
the two's list that's 3.6 meters
m is 4 and lambda is this value
413.5
times 10 to minus 9 meters
so 3.6 times 4 times 413.5
times 10 to the minus 9.
all of that is equal to five point nine
five four
times ten to the minus six
and so we need to take that answer
and divide it by four point five times
ten to minus three
and so the separation distance between
the two slits is one point thirty two
times
ten to minus three meters
and ten to the minus three is basically
a millimeter
so this is one point thirty two
millimeters
and so that's the separation distance of
the two slits
so remember for these types of problems
there's only two formulas you need
this one ym times d is equal to l
m times lambda and keep in mind you can
only use this
if theta is very small which
for these problems it usually is
and then the second one
d sine theta
is equal to m lambda
and you can always use this just make
sure that uh theta
is in degrees you could use radians too
but if it's in degrees this should be
fine
if you don't need the angle chances are
you're probably going to use that
formula
you